{
  "q1": [
    {
      "question": "A thinker from this country founded structural anthropology with works like The Elementary Structures of Kinship. Another thinker from this country founded a “religion of humanity” and formulated a “law of three stages,” espousing philosophical positivism. The Elementary Structures of Religious Life was written by a sociologist from this country who pioneered the field with a work examining suicide. For ten points, name this home country of the thinkers Auguste Comte, Claude Levi-Strauss, and E´mile [ay-MEEL] Durkheim.",
      "answer": "France"
    },
    {
      "question": "This man recruited Cord Meyer during a mission to manipulate the news media in Operation Mockingbird, and he assigned Sidney Gottlieb to experiment with the possibility of mind control in the MK-ULTRA project. When Mohammed Mossadegh nationalized the oil industry, this man launched Operation Ajax to place Mohammad Shah Pahlavi in power in Iran. This man earned the displeasure of President Kennedy after planning the botched Bay of Pigs invasion. For ten points, name the longest serving head of the CIA, the brother of John Foster.",
      "answer": "Allen Dulles"
    },
    {
      "question": "This event led to the formation of the Dewey Commission, which exonerated one of its victims. Other victims of this event were accused of assassinating Sergey Kirov and included the right-wing Nikolai Bukharin. A photo was changed after this event to exclude Nikolai Yezhov, who was responsible for the worst actions of this event. The NKVD carried out most of the executions during this event, which aimed to get rid of the supporters of Leon Trotsky. For ten points, name this cleansing of the Soviet government just prior to World War II.",
      "answer": "Great Purge"
    },
    {
      "question": "A scholar who lived in this city wrote The True Intellectual System of the Universe and was a rival of Thomas Hobbes; that man was Ralph Cudworth. This city names a group of Platonist 17th-Century philosophers and a group that included Anthony Blunt and Kim Philby, a spy ring known as this city’s namesake “five.” Isaac Newton attended Trinity College in, for ten points, what British city whose historic university is a rival of Oxford?",
      "answer": "Cambridge"
    },
    {
      "question": "Amphibious landings near this city were a key part of Exercise Zapad-81, the USSR’s largest military exercise. In January 2019, this city’s progressive mayor, Pawel Adamowicz [pav-el adam-oh-vitz], was stabbedandkilled.Shipyardworkersinthiscitychanted“BringAnnaWalentynowicz[vah-went-ee-no-vitz] Back to Work!” in 1980 during a strike at the Lenin Shipyard. The Solidarity movement began in, for ten points, what Polish port city?",
      "answer": [
        "Gdansk",
        "Danzig"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "In this decade, the Lafollette Commission revealed that the Pinkertons had spies in “practically every union in the country.” John Lewis negotiated the recognition of the UAW by General Motors after the Flint sit-down strike in this decade. Yellow Dog contracts were outlawed in this decade, in which the Wagner Act codified the right to unionize. The CCC planted trees to ameliorate the Dust Bowl in, for ten points, what decade in which Franklin Roosevelt introduced the New Deal?",
      "answer": "1930s"
    },
    {
      "question": "A theory about this man claims that he was shot while boarding the boat of Jakob Lidl. An unfavorable report from Bernhard von Gudden led Prince Luitpold to depose this man, who was found dead in Lake Starnberg after a possible failed attempt to escape captivity at Berg Castle. This ruler’s palace was located above Hohenschwangau [ho-hen-shvan-gow] and inspired the Sleeping Beauty castle. For ten points, name this king of Bavaria who constructed Neuschwanstein [noysh-van-stein], known as the “Mad King.”",
      "answer": [
        "Ludwig II of Bavaria",
        "Mad King Ludwig"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "Peter Greyson partially destroyed a copy of one of these documents by pouring red paint mixed with glue on it. The 7/50 formula concerns changes to one of these documents in Canada. The Indian version of this document is the longest in the world, and the American version includes a Revenue Clause, noting that spending bills begin in the House of Representatives. The Articles of Confederation were replaced with, for ten points, what type of governing law?",
      "answer": [
        "constitution",
        "additional information, like Canada’s Constitution"
      ]
    },
    {
      "question": "These people were the target of a seawall built by Pompeo Targone, which withstood an assault from Henri de Rohan. A leader of these people, Gaspard de Coligny, was killed on the orders of Catherine de Medici during the St. Bartholomew’s Day Massacre. These followers of John Calvin were stripped of their religious tolerance by the Edict of Fontainebleau, many years after it was first granted by Henry IV’s Edict of Nantes. For ten points, name this group of French Protestants.",
      "answer": "Huguenots"
    },
    {
      "question": "Negotiations for this treaty occurred concurrently with those of the Treaty of Hubertusburg. Charles III’s refusal to cede Cuba led to Spain relinquishing Florida as part of this agreement, which was largely negotiated by the Duc de Choiseul. In this treaty, Guadalupe and Martinique were kept by a party that ceded all of its mainland holdings west of the Mississippi River. Much of New France was ceded to England in, for ten points, what treaty ending the Seven Years’ War?",
      "answer": "1763 Treaty of Paris"
    }
  ],
  "q2": [
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The first ruler of this dynasty legendarily ordered his soldiers to raise copies of the Quran on their lances, in declaring a truce at the Battle of Siffin; that ruler later came to power after the Kharijites caused the downfall of his main rival. This dynasty fell from power after a defeat at the Battle of the Zab and the subsequent death of Marwan II. This caliphate was founded by Muawiyah after the assassination of the last Rashidun caliph, Ali. For ten points, name this Islamic caliphate that was ruled from Damascus and which preceded the Abbasids.",
        "answer": "Umayyad Caliphate"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Umayyads levied what specific tax on non-Muslim peoples in the caliphate, in return for relative religious freedom?",
        "answer": "jizya tax"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man was forced to appoint the maligned Carlos Navarro as prime minister after Luis Carrero Blanco was assassinated in Operation Ogre. This leader rose to prominence fighting Abd el-Krim in the Rif War before taking part in a coup arranged by Emile Mola. In the civil war that followed, this man managed to unite the Carlists and the Falange, leading Nationalists to victory over the Republicans. For ten points, name this fascist leader of Spain.",
        "answer": "Francisco Franco Bahamonde"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "The Rif War was a Spanish attempt to quell an insurrection in this African country, where the Riffians were essentially an independent people living in a Spanish protectorate.",
        "answer": "Morocco"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "One of this composer’s most famous pieces names an operation during the Blitz that destroyed much of Coventry. This composer commemorated a British triumph at the Battle of Vitoria in his piece “Wellington’s Victory.” Another of this composer’s works was dedicated “to the memory of a great man” after its original dedicatee, Napoleon, invaded Austria. That symphony was his Eroica. For ten points, name this German composer of nine symphonies, the last of which contains the “Ode to Joy”.",
        "answer": "Ludwig van Beethoven"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This Beethoven piano sonata, which was compared to the image of Lake Lucerne at night, was dedicated to a woman who may have been Beethoven’s “Immortal Beloved,” the addressee of an unsent love letter. ANSWER:MoonlightSonata(orPianoSonataNo.14inC-sharpminor;prompton“Quasiunafantasia”) (4) This man rediscovered a river formerly known as the Mauritius; at that river, his crewmate John Colman was killed via an arrow to the neck. This captain of the Half Moon met his end shortly after breaking camp at James Bay when his crew mutinied and set him adrift during his search for the Northwest Passage. For ten points, name this English explorer for the Netherlands who now names a large Canadian bay.",
        "answer": [
          "Henry Hudson BONUS: The Hudson’s Bay Company began in 1670 and primarily dealt in this industry, which employed coureur de bois in New France. ANSWER: fur trading",
          "equivalents, like pelt trading",
          "furs of specific animals, like beavers",
          "foxes"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "This man recited the song “What Do You Do With the Mad that You Feel?” in a Congressional hearing chaired by John Pastore, who declared this man’s testimony “wonderful” and said “Looks like you just earned the $20 million.” Tom Hanks will portray this man in a 2019 film, a year after an acclaimed Morgan Neville documentary about this man became the highest-grossing biographic documentary of all time. For ten points, name this sweater-wearing late children’s television host, the subject of the films, A Beautiful Day in the Neighborhood and Won’t You Be My Neighbor?.",
        "answer": "Fred Rogers or Mister Rogers"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Mister Rogers’ 1969 Congressional testimony sought to reverse budget cuts made to this non-profit, which founded and funds both PBS and NPR. This corporation’s support is prominently thanked, usually before the support of “Viewers Like You,” by many PBS programs.",
        "answer": "Corporation for Public Broadcasting or CPB"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "The Canadian hundred dollar bill depicts a woman observing this compound through a microscope. A scientist remarked that it had gotten “the disulphides right” upon seeing Dorothy Hodgkin’s X-ray crystallographic structure of this compound, which helped him confirm the chemical structure of this compound’s A and B chains. After blocking off pancreatic ducts in dogs, Charles Best and Frederick Banting used extracts containing this compound to reduce blood sugar. For ten points, name this protein hormone that is used to treat diabetes.",
        "answer": "insulin"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "This British biochemist first sequenced insulin. Dideoxynucleotides [di-dee-oxy-nucleo-tides] are used to generate DNA fragments in this man’s namesake method of sequencing DNA.",
        "answer": "Frederick Sanger"
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "C´ecile Renault was executed for being caught meeting this man while carrying knives. After the fall of this man, the Muscadins led the First White Terror to eliminate his supporters. This man created a holiday, held on the anniversary of the Champ de Mars Massacre, for his Cult of the Supreme Being. This man’s death led to the Thermidorean Reaction, and he was a member of the Committee of Public Safety alongside ally Louis St. Just. For ten points, name this Jacobin leader who led the Reign of Terror until he, too, was guillotined.",
        "answer": "Maximillian Robespierre"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "Robespierre’s Cult of the Supreme Being was meant to replace this first atheistic French state religion. This deistic Cult shares its name with an Age written about by Thomas Paine.",
        "answer": [
          "Cult of Reason",
          "The Age of Reason"
        ]
      }
    },
    {
      "tossup": {
        "question": "During the Revolutionary War, Edward Hand helped delay the British invasion of this state’s Throg’s Neck peninsula. At a battle in this state, the forces of John Sullivan faced bombardments while stationed at Battle Pass. The quote “I only regret that I have but one life to lose for my country” was legendarily given by Nathan Hale before he was hanged in this state. William Howe forced George Washington to retreat at a 1776 battle in this state that took place in King’s County. For ten points, name this state, the site of the Battle of Long Island.",
        "answer": "New York"
      },
      "bonus": {
        "question": "During a British withdrawal from Manhattan in 1775, this man led a group of volunteers, including Hercules Mulligan, in stealing more than 20 cannons from a battery on the southern tip of Manhattan Island.",
        "answer": "Alexander Hamilton"
      }
    }
  ],
  "q3": [
    {
      "category": "Supreme Court Justices",
      "prompt": "Name the Supreme Court justice who...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Currently serves as Chief Justice and was nominated by George W. Bush.",
          "answer": "John Roberts"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was the first Chief Justice.",
          "answer": "John Jay"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was the only President to later serve on the court.",
          "answer": "William Howard Taft"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was Chief Justice during the Brown v Board case and switched parties in 1962.",
          "answer": "Earl Warren"
        },
        {
          "question": "Issued the majority opinion in the Dred Scott case.",
          "answer": "Roger Taney , but be lenient"
        },
        {
          "question": "Argued that the 14th Amendment “does not enact Mr. Herbert Spencer’s Social Statics” in his Lochner dissent.",
          "answer": "Oliver Wendell Holmes, Jr."
        },
        {
          "question": "Resigned from the court in 1969 after bribery allegations led to impeachment hearings.",
          "answer": "Abe Fortas"
        },
        {
          "question": "Wrote “I know it when I see it” in his opinion in Jacobellis v. Ohio, an obscenity trial.",
          "answer": "Potter Stewart Army Group South"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Army Group South...",
      "prompt": "Name the army group south......",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Was part of what country’s Wehrmacht [vair-mahkt] and deployed by Adolf Hitler?",
          "answer": "Nazi Germany"
        },
        {
          "question": "Included hundreds of what armored tanks, whose IV [four] version was the most common?",
          "answer": "Panzers"
        },
        {
          "question": "Lost the Sixth Army in what massive 1942 battle along the Volga River in Russia?",
          "answer": "Battle of Stalingrad"
        },
        {
          "question": "Took part in what 1941 invasion of the USSR, code-named for a red-bearded ruler?",
          "answer": "Operation Barbarossa"
        },
        {
          "question": "Launched Operation Bustard Hunt in what region during the Siege of Sevastopol?",
          "answer": [
            "Crimean Peninsula",
            "Kerch Peninsula"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Fought in what largest tank battle of the war, codenamed Citadel?",
          "answer": "Battle of Kursk"
        },
        {
          "question": "Attempted, in Operation Blue, to seize oil fields in Absheron in what modern-day country?",
          "answer": "Azerbaijan"
        },
        {
          "question": "Was led by what general, who failed to relieve Paulus on the Volga but won the Third Battle of Kharkov?",
          "answer": "Erich von Manstein"
        }
      ]
    },
    {
      "category": "Central America",
      "prompt": "Name the...",
      "questions": [
        {
          "question": "Project completed by the US across Panama, linking the Pacific and Atlantic Oceans.",
          "answer": "Panama Canal"
        },
        {
          "question": "Sport whose FIFA World Cup qualifier instigated a brief war between El Salvador and Honduras.",
          "answer": [
            "soccer",
            "association football"
          ]
        },
        {
          "question": "Country where a 19th century civil war led the capital to be moved from Cartago to San Jose.",
          "answer": "Costa Rica"
        },
        {
          "question": "South American country that controlled Panama, its neighbor, until American intervention.",
          "answer": "Colombia"
        },
        {
          "question": "Panamanian dictator who was ousted by the US in 1989.",
          "answer": "Manuel Noriega"
        },
        {
          "question": "Colonial name of Belize from 1862 to 1973, reflecting its European controllers.",
          "answer": "British Honduras"
        },
        {
          "question": "Central American country where the US carried out Operation PBSUCCESS.",
          "answer": "Guatemala"
        },
        {
          "question": "Dictatorial family that was overthrown by the Sandinistas.",
          "answer": "Somoza family"
        }
      ]
    }
  ],
  "q4": [
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This artist, who appealed to Republican sentiments with his painting Lictors Bring to Brutus the Bodies of His Sons, produced a propaganda piece in which stones are inscribed with the words (20 pts)",
        "“Carolus Magnus” and “Hannibal.” This man depicted a revolutionary clutching a pen in his bathtub after he was stabbed by Charlotte Corday, then depicted his later patron (10 pts)",
        "crossing the Alps at the Saint Bernard Pass. For ten points, name this French artist who painted The Coronation of Napoleon and Josephine and The Death of Marat."
      ],
      "answer": "Jacques-Louis David"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This man was replaced in his early career by Don Carlos Buell after a visit with Secretary of War Simon Cameron convinced the general public that this man was insane. This man’s Special Field Orders Number (20 pts)",
        "15 was interpreted as a promise of “forty acres and a mule,” and he notably destroyed railway tracks by wrapping them around trees to make a namesake (10 pts)",
        "“necktie.” This man helped turn the 1864 election for Lincoln when he captured the “Christmas present” of Savannah. For ten points, name this Union general who led the “March to the Sea.”"
      ],
      "answer": "William Tecumseh Sherman"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) This battle’s winning side took the Boedromia festival, which celebrated Theseus beating the Amazons, and changed it to celebrate this victory. A delay in this battle was prompted when it was found that reinforcements could not come until the (20 pts)",
        "Karneia [kar-nye-uh] festival ended. The winning side in this battle struck after Callimachus broke a tied vote in favor of attacking, thus turning back an invasion sent by (10 pts)",
        "Darius the Great. Athens prevailed over the Persian Empire in, for ten points, what 490 BC battle whose result was reported by Pheidippides after running 26 miles?"
      ],
      "answer": "Battle of Marathon"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) The Canadian Norman Bethune was embedded as a doctor in this man’s army. This man was profiled in the most famous work of Edgar Snow. Five Encirclement (20 pts)",
        "Campaigns attempted and failed to defeat this leader, who compromised with an opponent after that opponent was kidnapped in the (10 pts)",
        "Xi’an [shee-ahn] Incident. This leader moved to a new base in Jiangxi during the Long March. For ten points, name this longtime Chinese communist leader."
      ],
      "answer": "Mao Zedong"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) A treaty named after this location formally ended a conflict that included fighting at the Battle of Fontenoy; that treaty dividing power among Lothair, Louis the German, and Charles the Bald. Fort (20 pts)",
        "Douaumont [dwoh-mohn] and Fort Vaux [VOH] were epicenters of fighting in a battle named after this location, where Erich von (10 pts)",
        "Falkenhayn failed to conduct a successful war of attrition. For ten points, name this French city on the Meuse River, the site of the longest battle of World War I’s Western Front."
      ],
      "answer": "Verdun"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) John Paul Jones created an unconventional variant of this object after capturing the Serapis. The first official version of this object was created from the coat of Abraham Swartwout, for which he was reimbursed. In (20 pts)",
        "1777, Congress officially adopted this object, which is celebrated on June 14th. While aboard the HMS Tonnant, (10 pts)",
        "Francis Scott Key was inspired by this object which withstood the Siege of Fort McHenry. Betsy Ross legendarily created, for ten points, what national symbol that inspired “The Star-Spangled Banner?”"
      ],
      "answer": "the flag of the United States of America"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) Housesteads is a particularly well-preserved fort along this structure, whose milecastles were typically flanked by two turrets. A series of tablets were found near this structure’s fort of Vindolanda. The River (20 pts)",
        "Tyne was the starting point of this structure, which terminated at Solway Firth. This structure, whose construction started in 122 AD, was intended to (10 pts)",
        "keep out the Picts and Britons from the Roman Empire. For ten points, name this defensive structure, built by a namesake Roman Emperor who succeeded Trajan."
      ],
      "answer": "Hadrian’s Wall"
    },
    {
      "parts": [
        "(30 pts) While vice president, a man from this state reported to Fort McClary to take over as his Coast Guard Company’s cook. John Nutting and John Calef led a British strategy to create “New Ireland” in this state. The (20 pts)",
        "Mulligan Letters helped tarnish a presidential campaign for a politician from this state. The Webster-Ashburton Treaty settled a war in this state over border disputes, the (10 pts)",
        "Aroostook War. The home state of Hannibal Hamlin and “Continental Liar” James Blaine is, for ten points, what state that was admitted to the Union in the Missouri Compromise, breaking off of Massachusetts?"
      ],
      "answer": "Maine"
    }
  ]
}